so what do you wanna talk about you said
something about wanting to go deep about
something or high about something some
kind of meta conversation or I don't
know IIIi didn't understand what you
mean I want to talk about I want to talk
about as a starting point I want to talk
about this notion so I've been reading
it oh yes therefore again me not to read
I don't know whether or not the
recommended or not it's this it's
intense shooting so tripper it's a he
was definitely a tripper and he
definitely does circumcircle ambulate
right it goes around and around
something right and it does something
does kind of like start to pop up after
a while but it's tough gone um but I was
thinking about like just this whole
thing about the this notion that he has
of like that the cell exists across four
dimensions and then speaks to you with
your conscience and your intuition but
which kind of presupposes some
directionality or an ideal which get set
the thing about the and again it gets
the thing about the eyes and how the
eyes move and that they're they're
forward-facing and the whole thing about
language and hitting the mark but it's
like the question I have is like what is
that that what is it that that knows to
do that I talked about that sounds
pretty cool well over are we recording
yeah sure yes we are okay cool well so
what are you thinking about it
it's let's see let's see if I can lay it
lay it out a little bit about about a
bunch of different things basically I've
been thinking about a bunch of different
things but meit's a lot of my thoughts
have just been kind of circling around
again and again this this notion or the
idea of the individual and especially it
it's actually in listening code Jordan
Peterson's talks especially the last two
or three have just been awesome I think
that I think they've been in like a
totally different like a very very
different level but I like the way that
he elucidates Young's notion of the self
it makes so much sense and I it's not
actually having me inspired to go back
and read and turn to tackle this one
just look at yeah I am this list but
it's it's it's saying when the way that
Peterson describes the underlying
underlying assumptions of your own have
it does have it does it does help me in
a reading reading the more complex stuff
that he writes like this but the see if
I can put I can lay it out as I
understand it it's like the yummie and
idea or young's idea of the self is that
it existed it is existent four
dimensions
and part of the South is in the present
moment and that that the the South as a
whole right you could say like the ideal
is you could say it's in the future and
beckons to us in the present via our
conscience and our interest that it
like what is it that it's calls your
attention forward and seizes your
interest and that basically the
development of character or the
individuation process is from Jung's
kind of motion is to continually make
choices and decisions and follow your
interest and over time make sacrifices
in your life and you begin to build
character and morality and make ethical
choices but the ethics and the morality
or the conscience or what draws your
interest to it is in some sense who you
would be if all like you can say is is
if all of your switches were turned on
and all of your software or realized
that that's somehow and this is like
fascinating to me is that somehow being
a self this idea of being a self or an
individual that there is this thing that
does call us forward right we know to
pay attention to certain things as
important and other things that are
important and I think that to a large
degree a lot of that stuff is a lot of
the content of that is given by a
culture but that we know how to do that
that we know to attend to something that
we know to value one thing over over the
over the next seems to be much deeper
and much older than just something that
you can kind of acquire like software
through culture seem to be kind of
bottom-up and I think that Jung's idea
was that is it the more that you can get
in touch with that greater self right
the more the more individualized will
become right the more that you can
listen to your conscience and listen to
the things that bug you and give your
give your attention over to things that
interest you in sees and the
easier attention it the more that you
can do that in other words the more you
can be yourself the more yourself will
manifest or the more the whole of the
suckle will make itself known so I
started it see what you thought about
that okay so to prompt you say a little
bit more the individual and the self so
what I sort of heard you say is that
that the more the self audience towards
the ideal the more it becomes an
individual so I'm curious like what's
the difference between an individual and
the self so um what I think you and
would say is it the South is is the the
south is is much older than you is that
it has a deep structure and then one of
the ways that you can notice or or
notice the evidence of that structure I
think he would say first is biological I
think the way he would put it is it like
it arises through biology there are
these basic kind of tensions I don't
even know if I can quite you have to go
pretty deep to come to understand this
but but basically you know through play
biology and then when we begin to use
language that the the basic structures
of language you can say arise from the
collective unconscious or from like a
deeper and deeper fundamental biology
and that you can see evidence of that
through myth and folklore and through
stories that you know for example you
know the resurrection is like one of the
that's the motif but like a mythic motif
that clegg exists across almost all
religion this notion of sacrifice right
and like you have to die to something
you have to die to something greater
than yourself so that you're born
right these are kind of like mythic
motifs and you can see them in in
mythology you can see them in fairytales
you can see other people's dreams it's
kind of like the deep plumbing or or the
motherboard right it's my understanding
of works the penis elephant and this is
the the motherboard with the deep
plumbing of the self
this set of archetypal figures or
metaphors that culture taps into but
there's a set of potentials on there or
the okay so the self is the set of
archetypal spaces or patterns that uses
culture to create an individual kind of
like the individual is the character
that the self creates this is this is
where this is what what I think makes it
an individual in this is is that that
deeper structure beckons our attention
right to certain deeper patters right
and that there is this kind of quality
with self-consciousness right or what
you would call you know that part of
ourselves that we are conscious of or
consciously aware of what you do you I
think you would refer to that is like
the ego is that the that the that the
individual becomes a true individual the
ego becomes individualized or goes
through the truth through the
individuation process which is to
discover more and more of its deaths
right to realize that it's not just a
single Island right floating separate
from everything else but it's connected
to everything else and that if they can
like get into conscious relationship to
the deeper parts of it that that
relationship will deepen its sense of
what if it can work one when its
conscious of and what it acts from
so I think it's more like a dance it
goes back and forth and I think that
that back and forth dance is if you
think about it what we're doing
constantly in our minds is we're
constantly rehearsing situations in
front of us
we're thinking about we're thinking
about things constantly well why are we
doing that you could say that that we're
you know what we're doing what thinking
does which which is you know why would
nature like create a nervous system that
then can abstract itself out and then
ply itself back to its own abstractions
and then and relate to that called
thought is it's it disengages the
biology and is able to create worlds and
then rehearse things over and over and
over and over and over again that
movement of rehearsing things what the
movement to do something that they gets
us to something greater or to move
towards something better that that that
movement itself is the CIM is that is
the is that is given by the structure of
the self right in that individual
process that whole movement ism is you
working out moral and ethical dilemmas
that aren't exactly obvious but you're
but that particular attention I think is
is what you're just kind of talking
about with it and that when you give
yourself to that the more that you can
give yourself to the ideal or recognize
the ideal within your own consciousness
within your own urges right in what
messes with you and what interests you
that over time that your life starts to
become you get this sense of your life
being kind of lived or connected to
something much greater than yourself
which gives a lot of meaning whatever
you are that's my understanding ever and
again to explore so one of the things
you started off is like that we can do
that right he's
Wow and what is it that does that so so
again to inquire a little deeper into
into what you're saying so the self you
could say is a set of constraints
desires urges archetypes that has a
sense of this higher deeper further more
true more beautiful thing called an
ideal or an ideal self but it's that
there's something in the self that
recognizes better yeah more beautiful
right and in moving towards that it's
confronted with the series of ethical
moral dilemmas you might also say
metaphysical dilemma this
epistemological dilemmas political
dilemmas aesthetic dilemmas right in the
five right that that there's a in order
to achieve a greater expression of the
ideal the self uses these archetypes
uses thought in mind in order to
envision a set of possibilities worlds
choices in a simmer Acula some kind of
mental world or projection and then it
then plays with this projection to
figure out and try to guess what's going
to happen in the actual world yep and
choose a path that leads towards more
and more beauty yeah higher ethical more
moving towards ideal totally and then
that one can add one more thing in that
that connection between the ideal and
the ego if you will right the
phenomenological self that I'm
experiencing right now and the ideal is
the connecting point is imagination
and I this is a really interesting this
is a really interesting idea
one that I think that I think that you
only talks about where is we say and we
know we know this because it's because
when your imagination moves it's when
you're at the edge of like where
something just starts to come into
articulation or just starts to come to
the form from from but it's not totally
revealed that's why I think space is a
place that universally human imagination
just go sports right outer space like
when we have a sense that there's
something we don't know what we know
where it is
or we have some form of it the
imagination just moves in to meet it
right so like any kind of you know
traditionally any kind of open space or
half or barely articulated something
when it's in the drift imagination moves
towards that incompletion and it's that
meeting point is you could say is that
it is the place where the self makes
itself if you will and therefore you can
collectively look at history and this is
fascinating
you can induce you know there's a
million ways to read history like one
way would be to read it as a serious
facts that happened over through time
but you could also be take this idea you
can also look at history as the state of
the imagination collectively
what as history moves itself forward
into the future it if that meeting point
is weird look if the future is the
unknown and and the present is known and
you're moving towards and expanding and
growing well its actions they're gonna
be based on what it imagines is coming
and that that imagination has a
structure so you can all you can almost
look at history as the collective
imagination the movement of the
imagination over time right which i
think is it's a I think it's a
fascinating idea when you think about it
like looking at it as a
revelation of the deeper structures are
the way that imagination moves which is
you know points to these kind of deeper
structures that you weren't authorized
yeah this peg alien notion this kind of
German idealistic that you could say God
is working out the ideas of the self of
what's possible for Humanity through the
collective imagination of humanity being
transferred and transformed into actual
infrastructure and societies yeah
absolutely yeah
Wilbur talks about the four quadrants
where you've got your internal thoughts
like what is the individual thinking and
then what's the group thinking what is
the individual say biology right and
what is the infrastructure of society
right yes all right and by playing with
this it's like the the individual pushes
things forward in navigates this dance
of imagination from who they are what
they understand themselves to be in the
ideal of what they think they could be
this somehow Talos towards which they're
called the great experience is more
beautiful somehow yes all right
their imagination in the face of that
thing first of all articulates what is
it what would it mean for it to be more
beautiful and creates visions of what
that is and then creates imagined
imagination visions of how we could get
from here to there and then judges those
imaginations is good bad better worse
according to the vision and so it has it
refines the vision it refines the
imagination which allows it to create a
better vision which allows it to refine
its vision more
you could say we communicate that with
others building communities those
communities build actual social
structures that drive that yeah / and
that changes the kinds of environments
that people grow up in and therefore the
kinds of original patterns they could
make until they actually start thinking
yes don't like so many fun places to go
absolutely and I think that that one of
the things maybe this will inform where
to go but I just thought of my dad used
to say to me when I was a kid he used to
boggle my mind a few questions you know
no surprise consider how it grew up that
the thermos keeps the Hot Stuff hot in
the cold so cold but how does it know I
was thinking about that that's basically
kind of s where a lot for me a lot of my
imagination awfully often moves towards
is this this thing about there's that we
value like there's what we value and
then there's like lots of arguments that
we can get in a debate about what is
better or worse but that we're inclined
to know that how do we know right how do
we know to do that a good a good kind of
grounding example of that too is what we
were talking about earlier today of the
example of the guy who recorded every
sound that his son or son or daughter
made as as they learned to speak and he
he was able to notice the pattern
underneath it and that phase that you
know when you babble it's obvious it's
all the basic funnel all the sounds of
every single human language and he said
that like the process of articulating
coming to terms right were these the
fundamental structures of language which
the the baby would go back and forth
back and forth and then it would
continually hone in on until the goddess
right that even good like before you
know you no one taught them don't
teaches somebody how to learn language
when you grow up you just learn language
but the look that I think that it's
fascinating that we just know to do that
but there's this sense of that there is
like there is a there is a a center or
there is a name and that we know to
orient around that and when we know to
perceive and feel into it and guide our
actions in terms of that aim is like all
the way down to like when were babies
learning how to speak we're doing that
the mad thing that that knows to do that
and whatever it's calling it forward is
that is the thing I would like you to
yeah and and I think I think I've said
this I think like what is what why is
that thing that way like why does the
universe exist in such a way that we can
have a conversation about the fact that
the universe exists right because it's a
particular kind of universe in which we
can have these cumbersome kinds of
conversations all right I don't know if
you've heard about the anthropic
principle there's the north and the the
weekend throught that principle and the
strong in topic principle and the
completely ridiculous anthropic
principle so this is just the basic idea
is you know why is it that we exist and
one way of thinking about it is that we
just happen to live of all the potential
universes we just happen to live in one
in which we can exist all right you can
look at that from a weak perspective
which is yeah it just so happens that we
exist in that well we can say well for
the universe to exist
right it's actually designed such that
we can exist in it
yeah totally it's so fine-tuned if you
change go down to the fundamental
constants if you change any of them a
little bit like the universe space
expands too quickly so that it doesn't
condense and things or it contracts too
quickly so that it doesn't expand into
things and this human organic life form
that is sufficiently complex that it can
become intelligent only exists in a
particular universe yeah right and it
could be to the point that Stephen
Hawking once intimated that like it's it
is in fact consciousness and this
intelligence that that the universe
sorts for so there's an infinity of
potential universes and the one that
comes into existence is the one that has
that well I wish I had not described as
the compute completely ridiculous and
profit principle or crap right right but
there's something about the universe
that causes human beings to be born in
such way that they truly non-language
yeah
they have the capacity to make you could
say every sound in every known language
right right they have the capacity to do
all of those things as babies yeah yeah
and then they're surrounded in the
environment of language in which only
some of those sounds are used so they
kind of tried them all right they try
them all and then over time and from a
biological perspective they actually the
ones that exist in their environment in
which they get rewarded for those
neurological pathways grow and the ones
that they don't use actually die off
they actually prune off the parts of
their brain the the motor pieces that
can make those sounds actually get
pruned off
hmm ready you true in on it you say it's
like how do you like it throughs in on
the perfect phoneme the perfect perfect
in what sense like what is the it that
it's zeroing in on it's whatever happens
to be in their environment right totally
and they prune off the rest and then
they become expert in making the
particular sounds of the language of
their particular culture yeah so you've
got this interesting thing which is
there's there's all these possibilities
each one of them has its own potential
legitimacy and the baby truths in on the
one that's going to work in their
environment right Hey all right so on
the one hand the fact that that happened
it's like what is it that causes that
it's we're in that kind of universe and
I don't have much like the rest of it's
pretty much beyond my paygrade like how
specifically does that happen you know
we're getting more and more senses more
and more understanding of the actual
biology can I ask you a question when
you say like when you say I like that
term by the way it's the unlike but
above and beyond my paygrade what is
your relationship to beyond your your
paygrade like do you have what is it I
mean I could imagine could be a kind of
complex answer but like is it when it
when it hits like the edge of what you
know that you can know for sure do you
have like what's your relationship to it
is it do you go like okay well I just
don't think about it or or do you like
to speculate or what's your relationship
to beyond your your paygrade
do it is there a simple answer to that
relatively simple okay great so I think
you you think you offered a kind of a
range of possibilities I do you just say
I can't get any worth I can't know for
certain and therefore I don't think
about it or do I like to spec
about it right and if we're to bring it
back to what you're talking about okay
so you've got this imagination and
you've got the world that you know the
ego the known right versus the unknown
of chaos and Peterson's language right
you've got the knowledge that you've
already got the comfort of the of the
structures that you already have in
place and then you've got the unknown of
chaos right but there's something in
that relationship between the known and
the unknown that you can see better and
that you're driven towards better that
there's this inherent Talos towards
beauty with goodness and the triad or
knowledge and justice if you add in all
five you've got these you've got this
there towards which you are oriented yes
right this built-in Talos somehow right
and in the face of you've got structure
the known and then chaos the unknown
there's something about the relationship
there were we dance an imagination
towards that Talos that beauty justice
goodness knowledge truth we we moving
towards that is fundamentally fulfilling
it gives us a sense of meaning and
purpose and direction and depth in
progress and movement right that when
that's fulfilled like our conscience
says yes that more and when we're off
track for that our consciousness goes
Eric like thrown through the like so
that that dance is in place so given
that you could say that there's there's
questions that I cannot be certain about
like I go oh let me examine that
question me personally let me examine
that question
given everything that I know I have
absolutely no means of answering that
question with with anything other than
speculation it just simply is enough
data to answer that question right
totally there for anything I have to say
about it is me just talking out my ass
right okay so what do I do in the face
of that yes yes right this is kind of
the question I hear you asking is that
yeah yeah yeah
so if I think that the speculation
itself is fun and the dance of it will
leave some kind of structures that will
allow me to create with labor right the
the classic example is fine fine Minh
was in the lunchroom when he was
watching kids spin their plates and you
know you spin the plate nikoline and he
went oh wow so he just figured out the
math on how to describe that cuz it was
fun it was fun for him it was it was a
challenge for him he's like yeah that's
pretty cool
great but it also knows that by solving
those kinds of problems he's leaving a
set of tracks in his mind that are
probably going to be useful for
somewhere else so he follows his
curiosity boom there it is where the I
with the understanding there's some kind
of track that's gonna be laid that can
be useful and he later used that to
understand some characteristic o of
electrons which you know is one of the
great leaps there were comments like he
took this wild speculation and used it
in another place so when I say it's
above my pay grade I mean I can't talk
about it with any certainty in fact I
can't even talk about it with any really
better than another answer answer right
there's a if there's like an infinite
spectrum of answers that are equally
implausible yeah and
even if I can say okay I can rule out a
whole series of answers the space of
potential answers is so large and the
ability to differentiate between good
and bad answers within that space of
potential answers I just don't think
it's gonna be productive for a practical
and so I've got better things to do with
my mind so and the actual speculation on
it doesn't seem like it's gonna leave me
with anything useful either right right
right
then I mean there there are times I
don't know some kinds of journeys that
you take where you just follow the track
wherever it leads and it and it's
fascinating in and of its own right and
it leaves no useful tracks yeah but it's
it's a thinking dead-end that doesn't
lead me anywhere and sorry my personal
thing is beyond my paygrade means that I
don't really have anything I think
useful to say about it and talking about
it isn't it's so it's so much in that
realm of there's nothing useful to say
about it that even talking about it even
thinking about it doesn't lead anywhere
productive and of all the places I'm
going to spend my time I don't write
alright and and the ultimate questions
of why does the universe exist why does
it exist in such a way that creatures
got built on it that can ask the
question why do you why does the
universe exist
yeah like whatever it is about the
universe that causes that yeah whatever
that causes it to be in that particular
way is in a realm
you know Kant talked about it as the as
the noumenon mm-hmm great yeah thing in
itself right the thing in itself and
while I have enumerable arguments
against Conte right the pointing to the
thing that we cannot know about it's a
fundamentally unknowable question as far
as I'm concerned that's beyond my
paygrade
right and there's really nothing I just
you know not that I haven't spent a lot
of time thinking about it I just never
thought and I've just never thought
anything that was valuable enough to
share right there spent enough time with
it that it's just like okay just that's
just beyond my paygrade right listen
this mechanism isn't gonna get me
anywhere anyway so wild little I like
what you said about the tracks being
laid down just I don't know what I liked
about it was as you're talking I just
got the sense of like oh yeah there is
this way in which something like
something like if you can go up to the
mystery right and then and then
speculate however or imagine or wonder
or be cute like let your curiosity go
that sometimes and it sounds like what
I'm hearing you say is like that there's
an you have an intuitive sense that if
doing this is exercising capacities
right in itself it's already valuable
for you right that like it lays down
tracks maybe not in a direct usable way
that you can see in that moment but
there's a sense that it that it's like a
you know what they say about like
meditation that like was at the end was
it a good meditation or a bad meditation
well that's the wrong question right
that you meditated that you practice is
the is that is the point of it is the
exercise of of actually meditating what
we'll so let's use that example as a way
of defining what I said yes no
absolutely not there's good and bad
meditation it's ridiculous what what you
want a trophy cuz you meditated like
well I did it therefore it's valuable I
don't believe that that's how the
universe works I don't I don't think
that God is giving you points for being
obedient
and the only thing that you're supposed
to do like like you can waste time so
the other part of this thing is in
imagining yeah there's a Talos towards
which we're moving and I'll say one more
thing about that CS Lewis thing goes
abolition a man might have been mere
christianity mere christianity starts
off and he talks about the fact that we
have moral judgments but we think that
there's a more beautiful more just a
more ethical a more knowledge a more
true like we think so something about
the universe has that kind of thought
exists so God must have that right the
God that created the universe in the
universe is an expression of God and we
are part of that yeah like the fact that
that exists says something about the
nature of the universe right it's built
in yeah yeah built in we didn't create
that we didn't design that like we
didn't go I want to zoom in on the right
phoneme that allows me to speak the
language so that I can survive in my
culture it's perhaps built-in yeah right
so you've got this thing that you've got
imagination and imagination is
constantly trying scenarios to see what
is more true and what is more false like
your true in your trajectory towards
that Talos and some things are towards
and some things are away some things are
better and some things are worse right
right by what standard do you judge
better or worse was it a good meditation
or bad meditation yes we can say that
that was it's the wrong question asked
that really all you have to do is
meditate because here's the because
here's the good bad better worse towards
the tailless away from
because as long as you are meditating
you're putting yourself in the space
where you can start to notice the
patterns of what's more true and less
true in the process of meditating you're
refining your mind you're laying down
the tracks even if you're not coming up
with the answer correct and so if you
meditate consider that a wind even if it
was shitty meditation right right but
the thing is that you can do shitty
meditation like you can actually go in
to meditate and meditate poorly and
create more tracks going in the wrong
direction and build bad habits that you
later have to deconstruct great so yeah
there's good meditation and there's bad
meditation I think we're totally right
this meditation is the one that actually
clears out your mind so that you can see
more of the talos so that you can tune
into more of your conscience so that you
can like okay great so now I'm gonna tie
that back in with the phonemes of all
the potential ways of being human of all
the potential ways of using your voice
you discard all the ones that aren't
true to your culture and you literally
prune out the motor skills and the
listening skills to notice them which is
you know which is why it's very
difficult for some people raised in
certain languages to learn how to speak
the other languages read it like one of
the one of the increasingly problematic
prunings that we do in English is that
we don't recognize tone we're really
focused on the consonants and the vowels
recognizing them but not the shift in
the vowel over the course of a word
right so in Chinese you've got this
four different tones you can write where
you're going the same tone and then odd
down and then up and then all up and
down all right so when you're speaking
on dying
like I can't do it I haven't learned
that but I've learned enough to know
that I can't do it
right I've learned enough to know that a
native Chinese speaker can say the same
took the same vowel consonant
combination varying the tone and I can
with my best absolute hearing I can
sometimes maybe sort of hear the
difference for different things that
they're doing and I can't even tell the
difference right
okay so let's use that as a metaphor for
human beings getting brought up into a
culture and losing access to chaos you
know right now we're in a very
interesting time socially from my
perspective and Jordan Peterson's
speaking about this a lot where there's
this idea of privilege first there's
this idea of institutional racism
institutional sexism which is okay in
our culture the dominant culture the one
that everyone who wants to speak the
language in a way that they can be
understood right disappears the phonemes
disappears the ways of speaking prunes
them from their mind so that they can
fit the cultural pattern to the green
that you don't fit that cultural pattern
you are seen as broken less than not
good all right and we could say the
domina is a the leading idea in our
culture right now is that white male
heterosexual right you know let's stick
with that for now but that is the true
phenome that everybody is supposed to
adjust their language towards right
and if you don't then when you speak
it's like you have an accent huh right
right and so we could say we're going
through our culture and we're saying
a-ha we want to expand the possibilities
of what is canonical and language right
so that what if you're not white what if
you're not male what if you're not a
heterosexual or cysts like how do we
create space for those things when the
culture has trained people to move in on
the particular pronunciation the
particular expression of self yeah it's
locked it's locked in and is canonical
of the the dominant lineage yeah right
and and how do you how do you
communicate that well one way of doing
it is to say the dominant lineage is
privileged and all of the other ways of
thinking about it or pronounce
pronouncing the self are marginalized
and so what we need to do is attack the
dominant position for being dominant and
bring the marginalized voices and
legitimize than marginalized voices and
say hello yes yes that sounds like a
good thing however now let's come back
to you there's the entire set of
possibilities for human language and
there's one canonical ones that people
learn to speak and if they don't speak
it they're considered to have some kind
of language to be less than in some way
but what about better and worse right
that's like not part of that like being
able to speak different words different
languages being able to articulate
yourself in multiple things is is better
than not and the way that we bring the
marginalized voices into the
conversation there are better and worse
ways of doing that
all right say Jordan Peterson is saying
the way that you guys are going about
bringing these conversations into the
picture into the conversation by
destroying the canonical the canonical
is canonical for a reason that's what
our culture's through these tens of
thousands of years in terms of creating
an ideal have brought it into this
canonical thing and that's what we've
built the entire culture around is that
Canon the way that you expand that Canon
the way that you bring the marginalized
voices in your Canon the way that you
create space for marginalized voices to
be in the Canon you have to do that with
some sense of grace otherwise you're
just going to destroy the cannon and
you're gonna end up with chaos right is
it would you say is it is it fair to say
that that in trying to destroy the
cannon right that that's basically
taking the worst part of that cannon and
and then and not knowing that it's
necessarily and the tap kids that's
basically kind of like isn't isn't it
would it be fair to say that that like a
lot of a lot of the social justice stuff
and the the riots and the protests are
about kind of in a certain sense are
like trying to in a certain sense
destroy something
it isn't that kind of like using its own
logic unknowingly wouldn't you say Oh
certainly yes yes certainly yeah
certainly there's a and there's an irony
in that
yeah right it's it's the the classic
example is that you know people are
using their iPhones to say down with
capitalism right there's an irony in it
like you're using capitalism to just to
destroy itself you wouldn't be able to
do the things you want to do without it
but you're gonna destroy it mm-hmm so to
take the worst of something and to
attack the
first of something without recognizing
its value this is Jordan Peterson's
thing like he says there's just no
gratitude right the that the fact that
we all live like even the poor amongst
us pretty much live better than 16th
century 15th century kings and royalty
like they didn't have running water they
didn't have like glass for windows air
conditioning all the technology all of
the wealth that we have that we don't
even think of we just take for granted
and then we look at the one thing that's
not there yet mm-hmm and then shoot the
whole thing and then shoot the whole
thing not recognizing that the whole
society is built on that one thing and
if you take that thing down it's not
gonna lead to better it's going to lead
to a crumbling and chaos and in that
current chaos we're going to regress to
lower levels yeah yeah we're attacking
the worst part of something beautiful
without recognizing it's beautiful we
are in in the classic metaphor we're
cutting off the branch on which we are
perched we're selling off the branch on
which we're perched right right yeah the
tree has some unfortunate
characteristics there are some dead
leaves there are some poisonous berries
like there or whatever it is and so what
we're gonna do is we're gonna chop off
the tree at its roots not realizing that
the whole thing is going to crumble if
we do that hmm I'd say that's Jordan
Peterson's main critique it's like yes
there's a tyrannical father and yes no
matter how you look at it there's always
some part of the father the existing
culture which is tyrannical
right no matter how good did you get it
you'll just refine your perspective
until you can find something wrong with
that right I say that that's asymptotic
but that's just the nature of things the
more you clean the room the more you
notice where it's still still dirty
we're in it the more you accelerate the
vehicle the more you reckon you come
across this limitations you can fix the
engine it goes faster sure and it starts
to wobble at a certain speed so you fix
the alignment so you can go faster but
then the brakes don't work at the faster
speed and the faster you go you keep
coming across the limitations and I say
that's asymptotic it just always happens
the morning so if you're going to attack
a culture you're gonna attack a language
you're gonna attack the canonical
version of something for its limitations
for its faults without recognizing the
value that it brings you're you're
cutting off the perch on which year
you're cutting off the branch on which
you're perched and so this imagination
thing this individual the self that's
recognizing how does it use imagination
to refine its vision and therefore who
it can be what it's moving towards and
how it builds the self how it builds the
story the character of who I think I am
moving towards this ideal given that I'm
inheriting a certain set of phonemes
like my culture has taught me to be a
certain way and that's a set of
limitations but also possibilities and
I'd say in Jordan Peterson says like
well let's look at all the possibilities
that creates like we have more wealth
than anyone in human history people
could not even imagine the levels of
wealth that we have right go back a
thousand years five hundred years even
300 years to imagine the level of wealth
that we have they would be like we are
Richard
all the dreams of avarice but we just
look at and go yeah yeah whatever
that's just the given now let's find out
what's wrong and we're willing to
sacrifice all the structures that hold
this thing in place yeah in order to
critique it that there's something
completely out of balance with that and
the self yeah totally individual in
order for the individual to move forward
in order for this to work better I don't
know why it's that way but in order for
it to work better in order for us to
move more towards the ideal and in the
process
imagine a self that we can then embody
and get better and better and better and
better
yeah like a fundamental piece is to
acknowledge all of the goodness which is
there acknowledge the tree in which we
are perched the branch on which were
perched the goodness that we are the
skills that we've developed the
capacities that we have at least as much
if not more than finding fault with what
we have yet to do with the problems we
have yet to fix in terms of the self and
the individual what is an individual
that we want to be right grades totally
fundamentally one of gratitude of
acknowledgement which is why I think
encircling it's acknowledging the person
as they are relating them right as they
are which is the fundament that allows
us to go into the realms of potential
shame to have people look at themselves
and recognize their limitations we don't
just focus on the limitations first we
make sure that they get seen and gotten
and acknowledged for who they are and
that creates the space in which working
on the next limitation is seen as a
growth rather than something that we
need to cut down further in order to
remake the system from whole cloth which
is never going to happen because it's
too damn complex
it's like trying to create a language
from scratch and they think what would I
think I think that that whole thing we
just described or like first acknowledge
right acknowledge everything that you
are and the uniqueness that you are and
and first and then that's important so
that when we look at the limitations it
is built its it implicitly has a sense
of a becoming of a unfolding of a
fidelity that pelos of a going towards
um and SAP that sounds a lot like
compassion yes to me yeah so funny I was
thinking that really reminds me of ein
rands keep context she says can't that
keep context yeah yeah like you have to
keep context like what is the context
that allows you to notice the problem
yeah yeah what is the mountain on which
you're standing that allows you to do
the problem I don't did you see the
deconstruction of the deconstruction
Wilfred Laurie
okay so Jordans latest saying I think he
heard about this morning here yesterday
he's talking with couple professors from
Milford Laurie and the professors like I
can't believe that people think that we
shouldn't do rationality that we
shouldn't do logic and evidence they're
actually questioning that right it's
like they're chopping off the tree in
which we in this postmodern move it's
like we're gonna question the standards
of logic and evidence and objectivity
mm-hmm well yes those are useful things
to question but from where you going to
question them you have to keep context
mm-hmm right like what methodology are
you going to use to question methodology
yes right as I you know I ran it's this
performative contradiction just post
modern performer contradiction it's like
to say that something's invalid you
can't say that logic is invalid because
in order to say something's invalid
you're invoking logic right it it cuts
itself off she calls that a stolen
concept right or a performative
contradiction yeah that you're saying
something which you can only say if you
assume the thing that you're critiquing
mmhmm yeah yeah in order to say the
logic isn't valid you have to assume
logic right in order to critically
examine rationality you have to have
rationality yeah in order to to discount
reality you have to presuppose it to
discount it yes you have to presuppose
the reality exists such that you can say
compare it with something to say that it
doesn't exists right it's so it's this
perform you have to keep context now in
human being we can call that compassion
because we have to acknowledge the
context of the person yeah to understand
their behavior and understand how their
behavior serves them or doesn't serve
them relative like their talos you've
got this imagination of what could serve
them or not serve them and to recognize
that relative to where they're at great
all right there's an infant like you
know I like to say that we live in a
state of infinite failure compared to
who we could be we suck Yeah right in
five years from now or a year from now
or ten years from now we're gonna have
gotten so much better
at the things that were really good at
now that we're gonna look back and go oh
god that was really embarrassing I
thought I was so good at that
and although I was relative to most
people and although I was relative to
who I was before given that I've got
five years more development in this I
look back on it and I sucked
totally and that's always the case
there's always a better
that you can move towards that when you
look back who you are sucks we're in a
state of infinite failure on all things
compared to who we could be right so
yeah okay yes we're failing great but
that's not what's important what matters
is what are we creating and what's the
next thing we can do we could always
point out to someone how they're failing
always but unless that's gonna serve
them yeah to actually get better unless
it unless it's on that edge of kind of
one I sort of know and you were talking
about this earlier it's like I kind of
know it but not quite here's an unknown
but I have a sense for the unknown I
have a sense that it is unknown and by
moving into that space I can use my
imagination to make sense of the unknown
to try out different possibilities to
imagine different things and then figure
out which one is better and then test it
and find out does it work or not I've
come up with a solution does it work I
can get better and better and better but
you've gotta keep context you've got to
stay compassionate to where the person
is so that you can point out something
that they can actually grow into rather
than just condemning them as bad right
how does that serve other than to get
power over them and is that really what
we want is really what we want power is
that really like the post-modern you
know again peterson says in the
postmodern thing it's all just
discourses about power right the
standards that we use rationality logic
those are all just mailed patriarchal
forms that we use in order to maintain
power really right are we gonna cut off
the whole tree because we don't like one
of the leaves we've got to keep context
we've got to be compassionate
two people that were speaking with to
the culture that we're living right it's
totally and what you're saying is what I
hear you sing as you're talking I'm
trading that the word dignity keeps
going through my mind about like what is
it to honor some dignity and I think
what I'm hearing you say is it's
essentially it's acknowledging in some
way or holding context right or or what
is what did you say and repeats and
contests keep in context right
keeping awareness of the context of what
kind of being you're actually relating
to which is that primarily the thing
that even has them make mistakes and
gives it as a mistake right is this is
this draw towards better is is that
there's a North Star in which has me
even take a scent in the first place let
alone stumble and do all the things that
I do that that impulse that fundaments
is core to being human and it's fun is
ultimately good and what I'm hearing you
say is like compassion is really holding
that context as primary which then since
its primary it will give every way that
you relate above it so the question I
have okay it's what is it that's going
on right now or what is it that goes on
that where it would make sense to not do
that like to like for example make these
kind of broad general sweet like notions
about like all logic is the patriarchy
it's like biocentrism in and all of
these kind of like like completely
nominal izing wiping things and just
basically assuming bad dropping context
not being contraction 't yeah yeah not
honoring the tree right that has given
birth to the branch right that has given
birth to the leaf that you've got a
challenge with right you know what
causes that
well what is it like yeah what is that
that's that's a broad question but like
what is the impulse to do the opposite
right we say good if the one's good and
the other ones bad or the ones good and
evil that particular fight that urge
there's some kind of pleasure there's
some kind of resentment or revenge thing
or something that seems like it's going
on it seems to be motivating a lot of a
lot of what I'm hearing about I mean
just you know I live in Berkeley and
there was a speaker that there was a big
protest going on who is for the most
part he was a look I think he's a little
bit middle to the little bit to the
right and that they had been at Berkeley
had him on as a speaker there was this
huge protest and I remember I had a
meeting and there's so many helicopters
circling around that literally we had to
speak up during the meeting and the
strangest thing is that the next morning
when I walked outside on the church
across the street
I'm on both churches on all the
buildings up and down the block was the
hammer and sickle sign was spray-painted
everywhere it was the strangest most
eerie feeling and I really got the sense
of when I saw that oh it's like two
things with your mind the first thing
was like really we we want to try that
again like 130 million people were
slaughtered by those governments right
first of all do we want like do we want
to keep trying that and the other thing
that I was like okay so given that I got
the sense that like I really didn't get
the sense that the people who were
spray-painting that even had a clue of
what they were spray-painting like I
think it was a little bit more I just
got the sense of like I I'm just
guessing but I don't have consensus
whether they're thinking like I'm for
communism based out of the like really
looking at what communism is and I
really believe in it enough examine it
there
for I'm sure those people probably
wouldn't spray-paint the hammer and
sickle on the on the wall maybe they
would but just I had that sense that
there's some kind of bigger thing kind
of underneath people that are doing
these kinds of crazy things I'm just
wondering what your what is that thing
that what is that thing that that is
motivating this like what do you think
this is what the leg is to consider the
question may be said watching your face
sooner possibly may be going on so
there's what it's like to consider the
question is it's not so much about the
question it's about what how the
question fits into our context into our
societal issues right because how I
answer the question isn't I'm just not
I'm not answering it for me and I'm not
just answering it for you I'm answering
it for those who wish to preserve the
tree while also enhancing the tree those
who are doing the hero's journey
according to Jordan Peters when you are
honoring the healthy father in search of
the healthy mother rather than battling
the healthy father putting all father
into tarana the father and all mother
into goddess mother right the people who
are really trying to move that forward
it's like I'm speaking to them as well
yeah and it's a very very difficult
question to answer because it's such an
ugly answer and in the context of
compassion that we've been talking about
mm-hmm the the answer of why that
happens what is the process by which
that happens it's both ugly and
compassionate like to understand what
what causes someone to spray paint a
symbol of communism
on buildings like what causes like what
is what are they sinking that they think
that that is the right thing to do right
when the compassion is that they think
it's the right thing to do like to
recognize they think that they're being
heroic but what kind of thinking has you
think that that is being heroic people
who are destroying ATMs and breaking in
windows people who want to smash
capitalism and literally smash it right
derekjjensen
very very provocative thank her you know
he says okay I can understand why you
don't want to bomb abortion centers why
you don't want to you know kill all the
people at Wall Street because you want
to take down capitalism my case he's
absolutely we want to take down
capitalism by force if necessary and it
will be necessary force is necessary cuz
they're not gonna give up their power he
says so
you don't want to kill all the you don't
want to blow up all the people on Wall
Street but you can certainly take down a
cell tower yeah yeah what is it that
justifies that kind of thinking where
you think that by destroying
infrastructure by doing graffiti of this
communist symbol that that is the
appropriate way to move the system
towards a more beautiful state
a more beautiful set of conditions and
this is where you know Jordan talks
about the kulaks where when the Russians
took over they went in the Ukraine and
there was peasant farmers who had
actually grown farms and they were the
successful farmers they were the good
farmers and they maybe had a couple
people working for them and they had
some stores and they got in the house
and they were the wealthy amongst the
peasants they were the successful
farmers and that the Communists came
along and said hey guess what those
people who are successful they got it by
exploiting you so we're gonna take it
from them
who responds positively to that know
what
well no no lots of people did and they
they killed the people and they took
their stuff and they sent them off to
concentration camps and that's what led
to the famine they killed six million
Ukrainians alright and in Jordan
Peterson Jordan peterson says now what
kind of people are gonna respond to it
he says now think about this you're in a
little town a little area and some
people are really successful and you're
not some people have successful farms
and they're building up and they're
becoming relatively wealthy we'd still
consider a complete poverty today like
according to our standards but
relatively wealthy compared to everyone
else and you have two reasons two ways
of explaining why they're wealthy and
you're not one is wow they must be doing
something right
what can I learn from them in order to
be able to build the kind of wealth that
they can build so that I can have that
kind of life or you can say they are bad
they've gotten it unfairly and therefore
I feel resentment for their success and
then
someone comes along and taps into that
resentment and says yeah you know that
resentment exactly
you should be resentful let's get them
all right so what is it that drives it
it's resentment right right
it's resentment you know a fundamentally
huh but like it's thinking that you're a
victim and therefore you can self
righteously attack other people right
and that's in what you're bringing to
light here is what I'm recalling is that
that one of them I think the most tested
on multiple levels of multiple cultures
mulcher in almost every single case the
difference between absolute poverty and
relative poverty where it's and you made
this a little bit earlier it's when it
keeps it up here a little bit like that
fat angler wherever there's a rich into
poor or there's extremes as well you
have you have to degree that they're
extreme right is to the degree that the
poverty the poor and at violence
wherever that's happening there's
violence the more that's happening the
more extreme it is the more violence
since it happens when everyone harshly
treat them yeah yes yes but however
mm-hmm
totally thoroughly however let's let's
go into a high school right some people
are more popular than others some people
are smarter than others some people are
prettier than others some people have
greater dexterity than others some
people can sing better than others every
single one of those forms clicks all
right people gather around those skills
and they attack one another for the
thing that they have and the other
person doesn't have
resentment is not just about absolute or
relative wealth wealth is just one of
the factors and if people are almost
equal and one person has a little bit
more relatively they're rich and if
resentment is in your character if you
have cultivated resentment you will take
any difference as an opportunity to
project yourself righteousness right so
it is true that the more extreme the gap
the more the more easy the symbolism is
but it doesn't matter yeah right again
if you go into any group resentment
raises its head right and this is part
of the compassion of human beings is
that where we I talk about shame and
guilt right there's the personal there's
what does this say about me what's my
status am I good am i bad mmm-hmm am I
better am i worse as a person and then
there's the practical is my life better
as my life worse right now these two
things that you got shame and shame is
horrible when like your identity is at
stake who you think you are hmm
when that's at stake you try to do
something to counteract that well and
that leads to resentment well like it's
like oh I have to be better than that
person so I constantly have to find
other people wrong so that I can feel
better
mmm-hmm to try to swage this feeling of
shame mm-hmm yeah right or I'm
constantly trying to prove myself that I
actually am better I get better grades
I'm dance better I sing better I'm more
popular I'm whatever it is and I grab
that as a way of differentiating myself
and make myself better
well to the degree that I'm feeling
shame I'm gonna build resentment and I'm
gonna attack others so that I can feel
better than them huh right to the degree
that I let go of the shame and this is
the personal development the
transformation to that you let go of
shame and circling we we see someone and
we say yeah that's who you are that's
okay really yeah Wow I'm free well what
do I want to do now I want to do
something better and they move from
shame into guilt into just making their
lives better looking for more wealth
more happiness more meaning prosperity
pleasure and purpose so it is true that
the more extreme it is the easier it is
for people to call on the symbols to
leverage resentment to build political
will yeah but almost all politics is
just about leveraging people's
resentment to create an other to create
an enemy so that you can create enough
solidarity that you can leverage them
for power and I think that's what's
going on much more than the extremes and
wealth yeah totally totally is I really
don't think it's about well it's really
not about inequality yeah
that's really not what it's about yeah
yeah that's just the thing that we use
to leverage resentment and by the way
the other thing about social justice
like you could say Marxism was really
focused on wealth and money on capital
how much money do you have right but
that wasn't enough to divide people so
we've started well know how much how
what's your race
what's your sex what's your sexual
orientation
what's your culture right we just keep
heightening the difference between
things such that we can find inequity
such that we can feel resentful such
that it justifies our self-righteousness
right and and people are just getting
flex in my perspectives totally people
are we feel shame they see yourself down
yeah and so they look for something to
blame for that right and then people
come along and give them a plausible
reason right the Communists came to the
kulaks tapped into the resentment and
and they killed and imprisoned people
and sent them away and they took their
stuff but that's fundamentally based and
resentment and I think that that like
that fractal perspective explains what's
going on
so it's an ugly explanation about why
people would paint why is it then ben
shapiro obviously a firebrand
provocative speaker i think that's a
variant protects the money would yeah
cuz yeah it happened with milo as well
but they didn't actually have the event
and so they weren't all the helicopters
and stuff where right he's provocative
he's conservative but he's actually a
pretty reasonable guy mmm-hmm right
there's lots of reasons to disagree with
him but to call him evil no that's what
that's like who are you talking about
yeah yeah and so to spray hammers and
sickles that's an expression of
resentment we can understand why they
feel resentful they're human beings we
all feel resentful and they're being
brought up in a culture that's
cultivating resentment great right and
so i can have compassion for them that
they feel resentful they're human
original sin we feel resentful it's a
useful metaphor in the face of the
unknown in the face of tyranny and them
in the face of being required to be a
hero and navigate that particular thing
burden of being yes yes yeah we were
thrown into this we didn't ask for it we
were thrown into this way of being into
this position of needing to be the hero
or
not huh the question is what do we do
with this resentment what do we do with
the shame directive 8 the resentment or
do we clean our room and take care of
our stuff and build our capacities do we
focus on
who are we relative to other people or
do we focus on the practical and learn
the skills necessary in order to be a
value and be of use to actually make a
positive difference in society by going
out and cleaning up the leaf if there's
a leaf there don't attack the tree go
get the lease yeah goodness this is so
this is so much I think what you're
talking about I'm really appreciating
what you're saying on a bunch of
different levels when I appreciate and
when I appreciate you holding context
okay in answering the question right
like that that to me just kind of that
you that you're grounded there and that
you considered that in answering the
question is demonstrating what what
we're actually talking about right in
that sense um totally appreciate that
the other thing and I have to have to
get going here we can we can pick us up
look if it was up for another time as
well is I'm wondering what the antidote
for resentment is and I it's so
interesting because I think it lies
somewhere in that in the strange way
it's like it seems to be it seems to me
that there's something like resentment
resentment in this way is almost like a
dyslexic it's like it's it's courage
it's a it's a a dyslexic courage right
it's like courage worn inside out right
because I think it's like to take on the
burden of being right which is immense
you're not gonna make it out alive
already one of the first things you
learn right it's hard there's all kinds
of tragedies that are gonna happen
guaranteed right
well what is it response what is like
pragmatically what's the what's the way
to set yourself up such that you can
make the most out of that
it's what's parent what's that what's
interesting about that is do the harder
thing right like like the not harder
thing in this case is to go out like in
like protest and unlike spray paint it
seems to me spray paint you know
communist signs all over the place
um that's more of kind of like the
easier route to take like the more
disruptive route it'll make things worse
but there's it's kind of like it just
seems to me that that and they think
this is what you was kind of talking
about a bit was was that if you listen
to your conscience
it will it will direct you towards the
the thing that's the most you know it'll
it'll direct you towards the thing
that's most true you up to usually the
thing that you don't want to do but that
if you did it
if he sacrifice the current pleasure
ultimately it'll you'll be rewarded and
that's true biologically right like when
we do something on earth I think you
taught me this right like um at first
ever since you said this you have your
to-do lists every time you do something
that is uncomfortable or hard and you
check it off you get a little dopamine
hits like I think that that's really
interesting that like our biology is
rewards us for doing something that's
actually more difficult than easy in the
long run that we can actually start to
be attracted to attracted to the thing
that's most hard and so my sense of it I
don't think that you know you can be
courageous and like towards the wrong
end so I don't think courage is like an
end in itself but it seems to me that it
seems to me that like the opposite of
acting eventually resentfully is is the
opposite of that or the counter move or
that would be something like moving
toward and understanding what I'm Lisa
about from its own position those kinds
of things like the things that like
where I seek to understand rather than
being understood I seek to know versus
being known that father father was to
see prayer know Saint Francis the st.
Francis birth okay but that seems like
something you choose to be too so the
word that I use that sums that sums it
up is responsibility
yeah it's to take responsibility for
what you are doing and what you are
creative it's to say that that which is
happening is an expression of you right
right verse it's - it's to be a cause
versus to be in effect you can say
fundamentally if the world is it fault
right then you're a victim and
victimhood leads to self-righteousness
when you declare yourself to be a victim
that means that there's a perpetrator
and you become self-righteous against
that perpetrator yeah right and that
leads to the whole cycle yes now you're
now you become a self-righteous asshole
you paint hammers and sickles on
buildings where you paint a swastika on
buildings same thing
currently st. curly so now you are the
victim and so you were self righteously
declaring attacking the perpetrator of
patriarchy capitalism whatever it is and
attacking it
but without and here's the main thing if
you're taking it as a victim from self
righteousness
but without a higher ideal that you're
presenting something else that you're
moving towards well the ideal is to take
down the existing it's to cut down the
tree we're gonna destroy private
property we're gonna take down
patriarchy we're gonna take down
capitalist we're going to take down the
bad thing out there versus
taking responsibility for what you
create with your life and who you are
what you do and how you impact people
yeah now you're at a place of cause
you're no longer a victim yeah so I
think we should start scheduling is the
key and that's the key that is the way
to take responsibility for your
experience for what you are going to do
and how you are going to live your life
not about how they are living their
lives and how we have to stop them
and here comes that here's kind of the
nobility of the individual of this is
the self from disease it's a record and
this you know it's the fundamental
heroic thing is that you become the hero
who handles their own stuff who creates
value doesn't destroy other things in
order to be more valuable actually
creates value in order to make the world
a better place like your kind yes you
show integrity yeah and that and that we
schedule we've scheduled more time for
these conversations right whether it is
really good this is such an important
conversation let's let's pick this back
up again really important all right rock
on brother rah what slow down